[SPEAKER_00]: A predominant view in modern Buddhism is that stream entry is a sudden experience, primarily seen as a culmination of one's efforts and meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the way you teach, it seems to be a much more gradual development, and stream entry is more of an irreversible and tried-and-tested conviction, rather than a special experience in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, when looking at the simile of days to be remembered by a king, and in contrast the simile of the axe handle, even the suttas seem to be divided on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could both yours and the common interpretation be right, or are they mutually exclusive?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, they are mutually exclusive, because those two similes are not actually at odds.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just like...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you think that one of them is describing... you already think the stream entry is an experience, and then you think one of them is describing an experience, and the other one is describing something else, then yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you assume that both are describing the same thing, and then the Buddha was referring to really one thing when he used the word stream entry, rather than two, then you would think, okay, well, these two things have to somehow be compatible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, yeah, it does say, like, for example,
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same way as the king would remember the day of his coronation, a person would remember the day that they attained stream-entry.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even says, like, somebody would remember, or the place where somebody attained the right view, they would, like, kind of honor that place, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a different sutra, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which kind of implies, like, yeah, there is a time and place where you would remember that you got the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you see, if you sort of go by what understanding is, which is what stream entry is, you would see that there is a time when you realize that you understood something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, after you've been trying again and again, for God knows how long, you were studying, sort of trying to wrap your head around it, some things made sense, other things didn't really make sense, it was obscured, and then you sort of tried and thought you'd figure it out, but then realized it doesn't match all this other stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, eventually, there comes a time when you realize, oh, okay, so this is it now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I started being completely in the dark about this, and now I know what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a mundane sense, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize both of those are true.
[SPEAKER_01]: You had to work in this very gradual way to wear away that darkness that you started with, until eventually you reach this point where you realized that you understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not that something happened and then, like, because of that thing that happened, you saw it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only thing that happened there is you did the work and eventually you realized that the amount of work you did was sufficient to reach a certain level of understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how both of those two things tie together.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, stream entry is knowing that you have understood the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just understanding the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, the person who, let's say, take a mundane example, started studying, I don't know, calculus, they can sort of have an experience of understanding calculus even early on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But are they sure that they didn't get anything wrong?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, are they sure that that they can now teach it to other people and there will be no mistakes in that in that kind of whatever they're conveying?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's knowing, being beyond doubt, that that which you have understood is the way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you have been trying to understand it long enough, and then... and that's also why you have this distinction in the suttas of the... well, later became sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Overly proliferated in the commentaries between the path and the fruit, that the commentary thought it was like, oh, the the path is like the whatever nanosecond, or whatever you want to divide it in, and then the fruit is whatever comes afterwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, you're never actually in the path.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have the fruit, because it comes immediately after.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the suttas, it would describe how somebody would... For example, you would be dhammanasāri or sadhanasāri, meaning
[SPEAKER_01]: You understood the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, you have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're unable to lose the right view, but you haven't abandoned the fetters yet, because you're not free from doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, imagine, like, somebody who actually has the right understanding of calculus, but they're still sort of, like, in that phase of, like, they just don't feel that they understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They haven't realized that they got it right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the fruit of stream entry, which is, again, the abandoning of doubt, knowing that it is that way, basically, which is what really counts as understanding, is what abandons these fetters and is what gives rise to that confidence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could say that realization the same way as you would remember, oh, that was the day that I realized that I understood calculus, having worked at it for two years before.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same way, the day that I realized that I understood the dhamma, having worked at it for probably even more than two years.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, yeah, like, how could an experience
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, imagine... try to imagine that, like, you don't know anything about calculus, but then there is an experience, something that you will see, that will replace all that work of studying and making mistakes and just, like, working through the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just, like, how... that doesn't... because that's not what understanding is.
[SPEAKER_01]: A picture, a thing, cannot give you understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's all these ideas, basically, just people taking the word understanding, mystifying it into something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just a vision, or an event.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, that's why you have all these views about, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would also have different teachers saying completely different things about what it is that you see when you get the right view, which is even more, like, doesn't quite match.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, then, if it's a picture that you can...
[SPEAKER_01]: Some sort of event that happens, then, yeah, it could generally be different, and you... and it could be an individual truth, because he saw this, he saw this, he saw this, and factually they all saw it, which means, like, that's right to that extent for each of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But an understanding either matches how things are, or it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means there is no individual truth on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's either right, which is you see the way out of suffering, and you are actually able to, by following that path, be completely free from it, or you have entered a path that, if you were to follow it, doesn't lead to the ending of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why even in the... when the Buddha was talking about his former teachers,
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't say like, oh, well, because, you know, they were sincere practitioners and they were really going at it, like they sort of discovered their individual truth, but I'm gonna find mine now.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said like, no, as far as they went, this is not the way out of suffering and that's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because, yeah, it's not about like, sort of conceit or anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, again, completely impersonally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does this, is this calculation correct?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, is this whatever formula that you used actually going to help you calculate the acceleration of something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is it going to give you a number that's just going to make you, I don't know, crash and not be able to build a proper product?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it either works or it doesn't, when it's understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I mean, many people would go after these kind of experiences then as well to check with somebody else if they are actually a genuine experience, if it was a genuine experience, so that can show as well that it's actually not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then other people would describe it as a sensation, you know, the coolness that they experienced, the easing of a burden that they carried around their whole life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but you see, all those are experiences, which again, it's it's not like somebody who is practicing would experience calm, would experience a peaceful mind, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, none of that is understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those things can make you more confident about your understanding, but they could also come from completely wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could feel calm because you think you're connected with God.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that mean it's correct?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just because it feels calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like... and that's why also you have all these suttas talking about wrong view, wrong intention, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong samādhi, wrong knowledge, wrong liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the way up to liberation, it can be wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: If your view is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not that because you feel a release... Like, it's not that a release proves its accuracy.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can have a wrong release, a wrong burdenlessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not... you don't understand what craving is, you don't see it for yourself, which means there is craving in regard to that experience, and it's like in the dark, not seen as an issue, not seen as the thing that's binding you still to some level of saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's not like you can sort of take that and sort of improve on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a dead end.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the assumption that you're working with there, that would have allowed you to reach those things, is that, see, it's not really important whether my intentions are affected with craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is that they result in this experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the whole thing was driven by that view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you get there, and you think, okay, that means I'm pure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that that is what took you there, means you didn't understand what craving is, and then there is no way that you can actually free yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no way that you can free yourself from existence, if you don't see what's binding you to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's... the Buddha gave it as like a... like a... almost like a logical sequence of events.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you have wrong view, for one who has wrong view, wrong intention arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: For one who has wrong intention, wrong speech, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like... it's... it has to... to... you have to actually accept
[SPEAKER_01]: It's better not to have calm experiences, if I'm actually... if that means that I have to reckon with this uncertainty about what craving actually is and how I can overcome it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's like, yeah, you can take a medicine that removes the symptoms, immediately, not feel them anymore, or something that doesn't quite remove the symptoms, but is actually addressing the root cause, and makes you feel bad for years, for as long as that root cause hasn't been eliminated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the factual or the wrong liberation that they factually experience, is not that it's
[SPEAKER_01]: Not liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that it's not liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it is a liberation of some sort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that they make it up or that they experience something wrongly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is actually a factual liberation, but it's just wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, it's important to see, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a dead end.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, because when you reach that point, and you think it's a liberation, well, it is a liberation in a way, but you haven't understood what craving is, and it's sort of floating around there, starting to practice would mean giving that up, because now that's where your craving is established.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you continue it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, yes, you haven't... let's say you won't return to sensuality, you won't return to these coarse things, but the craving is being allowed to survive just because you are still adhering to the strong liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why it's not like, oh, it can be sort of a stepping stone to the other thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, if you actually take on the right practice, you would drop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why all those ascetics in the suttas, like, when, let's say, they were not so far off, even then, they completely gave up their old teachings, ordained under the Buddha, and basically started from scratch.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the only, like, if you were now starting to take the craving as your criteria, you realize, I can't do this anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can sort of translate it, because it's about the craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you think that it translates still, it's because you still think, oh, it's the experiences themselves that have some sort of value in themselves, as if that's what the Buddhist teaching is about.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, it's about freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: The qualities that you develop through applying your mind over years to a meditation technique... Yeah, but qualities that, see, are... were all underlain
[SPEAKER_01]: by this wrong motivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the same as like, course example, but let's say you kind of quit partying and drugs and all that stuff, because you really dedicated to your work.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you replace that craving with a different one.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's absolutely not the same as somebody who gave up partying by giving up partying.
[SPEAKER_01]: And actually, there's a sutta that talks about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, he gives up killing by giving up killing.
[SPEAKER_01]: He gives up...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's Majjhima 54, something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He gives up in celibacy by giving up in celibacy, not by taking up something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because only then is it actually wearing away those tendencies that the mind has.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, the retort to this would be, well, but didn't the Buddha say that you give up craving by...
[SPEAKER_01]: Through craving, you give up craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, but through craving, you give up craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not through craving, I engage in another form of craving that I hope later will result in me being free from craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you are trying to give up craving now, in whatever form it takes,
[SPEAKER_01]: And yes, you will need some amount of craving for, like, some amount of motivation to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you are trying to give it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not just like, okay, well, fine, it kind of is there, but then it will go away later on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why that whole path that the Buddha taught of like suffering... sorry, right view and so on, like, it's very common to sort of think it's okay, it's these kind of states and practices and ways of seeing things that you can sort of just distill and just give to anyone and they can adopt them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the whole thing, the whole thing is what it is, because of that perspective that sits at the foundation, that craving is the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that perspective is not there, the whole thing collapses.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's leading to something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it makes you come.
[SPEAKER_00]: But wouldn't that criticism apply in the same way to the alternative, which would be like practicing the gradual training or training oneself in the gradual training?
[SPEAKER_00]: That can be picked up equally wrongly as a technique, as an external instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: While overlooking the foundation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, see, even the graduate training, like, when this is described, it's like, the person who would succeed in the first step, they would already have the noble aggregative virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in order for it to be the graduate training, like, that actually leads to nibbāna, you would already need to have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, really, it's more like you take on the precepts so that you don't do things that make things worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you still have to work towards that perspective that will make that practice right.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will sort of bind it all together and make it that you're actually giving up greed by abstaining from these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not giving up greed unless you're seeing greed, even if you're abstaining from things rooted in greed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, see, yes, the same exact practice, externally, could coexist with those very different points of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, one person could be keeping the precepts with that perspective that, well, any craving is the root of suffering, any craving is the reason why... it's my enemy, basically, it's the reason why I'm practicing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they would see, well,
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm abstaining from breaking the precepts, because that's rooted in craving, but then they would see all these impulses that would usually arise when people start keeping the precepts without the right view, to like sort of intensify, add more observances, add more rules, add more things that will make you feel safer.
[SPEAKER_01]: A person who's operating with that right perspective would see, wait, this is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: I shouldn't give in to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I shouldn't give in to breaking the precepts either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because both are rooted in craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you arrive at the middle way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, you don't do either of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, the lust is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: The restlessness, the doubt, is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you're not operating from that perspective, and you have this kind of abstract idea of renunciation, that, like, okay, it's giving things up, whatever internal state that involves, then, sure, you're giving the lust, but what about the other half?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, it's not the middle way anymore, and it's not going to lead you to the extinction of suffering, because that fire, it's just being given different fuel now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not even gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, then, right view would transform, even though nothing would change externally in your adherence to the precepts, but it would transform the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you would be free from sīlavata paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would be free from the self-view that also is inherently tied with that virtue as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, me as the sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: A certain identity, let's say, of upholding those observances well enough and stuff, which you would hear that and it would sound like, okay, so then you sort of don't identify with it, which means you sometimes break it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's because it's the middle way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's neither of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the emphasis in the beginning is more about abstaining from certain things, rather than doing things which are informed by the wrong view, by the wrong perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would bring you closer, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you kind of recognize it's not about anything that you do, as in like, okay, let's say I'm celibate, but then I also make a practice of every single day just reminding myself, like, of why I should be celibate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, see, that... it's not that that practice is bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha might even have talked about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, you are doing it in a way that excuses this clear unwholesome state.
[SPEAKER_01]: It basically justifies itself, regardless of whether there is any lust or not, which there may not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, that's what the Buddha meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you give things up without taking up something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the wise man does.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fool takes up one thing to replace the other one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I'm the person who judges that I know what the practice is, that I have the right view, how do I make sure that I really know and not delude myself into knowing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Probably the first thing is to ask yourself, like, why do you want to be sure that you know?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, if you're trying to find the certainty...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's very different from actually being unable to doubt, because inability to doubt does not depend on you deciding that you do have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... it's like if you're able to leave it ambiguous and not have to to come to an answer to it, then... and not be bothered by that,
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you are also aware that you have abandoned all these things, then, let's say, that's closer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, at the end of the day, well, yeah, you can always elude yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, all these...
[SPEAKER_01]: I've been mentioning a couple of times now, all these teachers that the Buddha had before, they genuinely thought, and they even described themselves as Tathāgata, sometimes, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the one who is gone, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how could... See, not even then, there was not even an external criteria that could have saved them, because the dhamma was just not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But fortunately, see, you do have an external criteria that you can apply internally, that you can see to be true internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what we said before in a previous talk, which is like, do I still suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you see, it's easy to sort of... it's inevitable almost to sort of descend into these... more of the emphasis on what you understood, and how far you came, and basically focusing on all the positive things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not seeing the massive garbage that might still be there, of things that are still clearly evidence of you not seeing the way out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for example, being challenged.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a common one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like when people would think that they have the right view, but then somebody challenges that, and they automatically feel like a need to defend it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Satipaṭṭhāna is certainly not free from essential desire, ill-will and all these things, but there's a crucial difference between that and what people who think they're satipaṭṭhāna usually think, which is, it's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I'm a layperson, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you would see all these these kind of threads of like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody actually sees for themselves that craving is the root of suffering and they're beyond doubt about this, beyond doubt, would they be able to see the most obvious form of craving in their lives and still not think that they have to give it up?
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that's independent of whether they actually do give it up, as in they have enough diligence to go against their own desire, but the fact that they try to justify it or try to, like, not feel like it's an issue, for example, that already casts serious doubt on that understanding, because that means you're not beyond doubt that craving is the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, yeah, you kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's say, if you want to doubt it, and you want to prove that it's wrong, you will be able to, because there are all these kind of different angles that even the Buddha gave in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're really honest about, like, you want to prove yourself wrong, basically, because you're rightly scared of that trap of thinking that you know what you don't, which the Buddha said is, like, destroys you, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you will be coming at it from the opposite perspective, rather than trying to find how many suttas I can see to validate my experience of satipaṭṭhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be looking at it like, no, I don't want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to find evidence against this, basically, because if I can find evidence of more work to do, that's only going to be in my benefit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and that's why, like, at the end of the day, it's not even necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that it gives you something special to know that you're a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the Buddha didn't talk about those distinctions in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: He revealed that later, towards the end of his life, in fact, when people were asking him about the rebirths of some of his disciples.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, in a way, it's better to just keep that clarity of, do I know that I'm liable to suffering still?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it doesn't matter, as the Buddha himself said, it doesn't matter if it's a literal or a lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same way as excrement, all of it smells equally bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you see, it all comes down to that sense of urgency that, like, that has to be triggered by, as I said before, seeing the real living sufferings that you're still subject to.
[SPEAKER_01]: The real shortcomings that you still have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not minimizing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not saying like, oh, well, see, I had this great experience and sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Automatically, you focus on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You immediately... You can't, at the same time, recognize all the stuff that you're still liable to, all the stuff that you haven't developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, keep that as a rule of thumb.
[SPEAKER_01]: Always focus on the shortcomings, on the things that you haven't developed, on the things that still pressure you, on the things that still trigger you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the Buddha himself said.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said he
[SPEAKER_01]: There were two things that that he came to know in the process of becoming a Buddha, and it was non-contentment with actual wholesome states, like things that he knew were wholesome, not even like, oh, I feel this, had this experience and feels good, therefore must be wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The actual wholesome things, and then relentless striving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, there is no benefit at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how far you went,
[SPEAKER_01]: To be to be content with, to be complacent, and to start kind of slowly devaluing and de-emphasizing all the drawbacks and all the imperfections that your current state of being still has.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the end, it boils down to not really being concerned about or defensive if one has the right view or not, but keep applying the question of am I still suffering and trying to uncover whatever is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, but at the same time, you have to keep in mind, you have to question your own views about what suffering is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just say, oh, am I liable to suffering and then take for granted that what that question is going to point to in yourself is accurate and and it's like, oh, I have 50% left and that's that's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like that very place that you're looking to find the suffering might not be the right one.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you see, that's one thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The other thing is like, if you're subject to craving, you will be suffering anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, you can know that you suffer, that's for sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You may not be able to pinpoint what that suffering is, why that suffering is there, how to put an end to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you just sort of leave it on that ambiguous level, don't overly kind of insert the explanations into it, you can see, yes, I still suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you keep that as the background and you see, okay, I have to tweak and upgrade and seriously question even my views about what suffering is, knowing that on that vague level I still suffer, but I just don't understand even that enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I know that it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you would be kind of progressing in the right way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, you know that there's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in the same way as like the example of studying a mundane subject.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know that you don't understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you also know that you don't know how much you don't understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just this kind of vague impression that I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you are willing to question basically every assumption you have about that subject, which is how you become an expert at anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if if you if you could kind of don't catch yourself drifting into that sort of taking for granted of little assumptions that you started with,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you would carry that, like, with you, indefinitely.
[SPEAKER_01]: And see, it's not like with some, I don't know, carpentry or something, with like, you can meet a professional carpenter and he can visually show you that you're doing something wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here, nobody can tell you, because you might, again, you might even be calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, wrongly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not even like there would be these super coarse signs of that you're doing something wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you would have to
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to have that, as I said, that drive to find the drawbacks, to find the imperfections and actually... actually feel a sense of fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that's what the sense of urgency is, saṃvegā.
[SPEAKER_01]: In fact, the word for fear and the sense of urgency, sometimes it's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's used the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it has to be like existentially touching you, that recognition of I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rather than like, okay, I don't know, but like, ah, it's fine.